President's Special Committee to Review the Undergraduate Experience; Records ua010.008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
President's Special Committee to Review the Undergraduate Experience Records
1974-12-1977-09
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua010.008
0.97 cubic ft.
Contains documents related to the Special Committee tasked with revising undergraduate curriculum during the 1976-1977 academic year.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Arrangement
Collection was maintained in the original order after it was transferred.
Administrative History
The President's Special Committee to Review the Undergraduate Experience (SCRUE) was created with the intention of reforming the university's undergraduate curriculum by defining undergraduate degrees and creating more structured programs of study. The Committee's ultimate proposal would be based heavily upon a similar program being implemented at Middlebury College of Vermont at the same time. Recommendations would include the reimplementation of general education requirements outside of the student's degree program and an increased emphasis on writing assignments through the university. The committee's report was presented in 1977 May.
Scope and Contents
The contents of this collection relate to the review of the university's review of the undergaduate curriculum with material from 1974 through 1977. Contents include: Correspondence between committee members and curriculum creators at other colleges, committee meeting minutes and related meeting memoranda, news clippings related to the topic of undergraduate experience, student surveys and correspondence between the committee and specific departments on the topic of course distribution.
UAlbany Presidential Offices; Curriculum planning
- Student Questionnaires, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SCRUE: Proposals and Suggestions for the Undergraduate Experience, 1977 April (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Special Committee, Background, (Outside documents) From various other universities, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SCRUE: School Course Requirements, 1975 November; 1976 October-November; 1977 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SCRUE: Middlebury College Newsletter, Course Catalogue, 1976 Fall; 1977 July; 1978 Spring (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Newsclipping on Undergraduate Experience, 1976 September; 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SCRUE: Final Report, 1977 Spring (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memoranda for Undergraduate Experience Meeting, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- SCRUE: English dept. questionnaire and memo concerning English requirement for the undergraduate experience, 1976 February (Box 2, Folder 2)
- SCRUE: Liberal Learning "A Real Conception of What Learning Is", 1976 December; 1977 March (Box 2, Folder 3)
- SCRUE: Depts.: Afro-American Studies Philosophy Theatre on distribution requirements, 1976 October-November (Box 2, Folder 4)
- SCRUE: Information from other State Universities on Undergraduate Experience, 1975 February-March (Box 2, Folder 5)
- SCRUE: Dept. of Humanities Response to distribution Requirement, 1976 October-November (Box 2, Folder 6)
- SCRUE: Dept. of Foreign Languages Response to 'Cure' Proposal-Dec 1, 1976 Language Courses and Professors, 1976 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- SCRUE: Notice and Agenda's of Meeting, 1976 September-1977 May (Box 2, Folder 8)
- SCRUE: From Office of the President: Emmett Fields regarding the Undergraduate Experience, 1976 May-September; 1976 October-November; 1977 January (Box 2, Folder 9)
- SCRUE: Chairperson for Undergraduate Experience: Ray Ortali, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- SCRUE: Guidelines for undergrad Education Report of Academic Credit for May 75, 1974 December; 1975 November (Box 2, Folder 11)
- SCRUE: letters from Chairman Ray Ortali on subject of undergrad. Experience March 76, 1976 May-1977 June (Box 2, Folder 12)
- SCRUE: Report from special committee of undergraduate experience to college of Arts and Science, Response to Report from Dick Collier and Report of Cornell University College of Arts and Science, 1977 January-May (Box 2, Folder 13)
- SCRUE: Minutes from Meetings, 1975 November; 1976 September; 1977 May (Box 2, Folder 14)
- SCRUE: Minutes and literature regarding, news clipping, The Undergraduate Experience, 1976 November; 1977 April; 1977 May (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Curriculum Development, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Letters and Memorandums on Academic Concentration, 1977 March-May (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Responses to Letter of 1976 October 25, 1976 October-November (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Answers to Document of 1977 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 3)